Well, thank you for coming along for week two, day four.
2주 차, 4일째에 함께해 주셔서 감사해요
We have lots of good stuff in store today.
오늘 멋진 걸 많이 준비했어요
It's another day of levelling up, of building new skills that adds to your capabilities of using Llms
오늘도 레벨업의 날입니다 중요한 비즈니스 가치를 창출하는 Lms를 이용해 여러분의 역량을 향상하는
for generating important business value.
새로운 기술을 개발하는 날이죠
As always, a quick recap of what you can do already describing Transformers and the terminology involved.
늘 그렇듯, 이미 할 수 있는 일을 간단히 요약해보죠 트랜스포머와 관련된 용어를 설명하세요
You know it well.
잘 아시네요
Confidently coding with the APIs for the top three frontier models, and now most recently, building
상위 3개 프런티어 모델을 위해 API를 자신 있게 코딩했고 최근에는 챗봇 비서를 제작했습니다
a chatbot assistant, an AI chatbot including an interactive UI.
대화형 UI를 갖춘 인공지능 챗봇이죠
And you're very familiar now with that messages structure going into OpenAI and with the way that the
이제 OpenAI의 메시지 구조에 아주 익숙해졌죠 그래디오를 위한 채팅
chat function works for Gradio.
함수가 어떻게 작동하는지도요
So today is about these things called tools.
오늘은 도구에 대해 알아보죠
By the end, you'll be able to define them, you'll have common use cases for them, and you'll be able
결국 정의도 할 수 있고 공통 유스케이스를 갖게 될 겁니다 도구를
to code an AI assistant that uses tools.
사용하는 인공지능 보조도 코딩할 수 있고요
Let's get to it.
Get it, get it 해 보죠
So what are tools?
그럼 도구가 뭘까요?
So it allows frontier models to connect with external functions with functionality outside the frontier
즉, 프런티어 모델은 외부 기능과 외부 기능성을 연결할 수 있죠
model.
도구의 의미는 그보다 더 광범위해요
It can be other things too.
다른 것도 가능해요
But most commonly, when you hear people talk about tools, it's in the context of giving frontier models
하지만 보통 툴이라고 하면 외부 기능에 접근하는
access to external functions.
개척자 모델을 뜻하죠
It allows for a richer replies from an LLM by extending its knowledge, um, it can carry out advanced
LLM의 지식을 확장함으로써 더 많은 회신이 가능하게 합니다 응용 프로그램 내에서 고급 액션을
actions within your application, and it can enhance its abilities by, for example, giving it a calculator.
수행할 수 있고 성능을 향상할 수도 있습니다 예를 들어 계산기를 제공할 수도 있죠
So as I said at the end of the last time, this might sound very mysterious.
지난 시간에 말했듯이 아주 신비롭게 들릴 수도 있어요
How exactly what exactly is going on here?
어떻게 어떻게 된 거죠?
We're going to build something like a calculator, like a function that can do calculations, uh, even
계산기 같은 걸 만들어 보죠 계산을 하는 함수요 일종의 파이썬
go as far as to do a sort of exact of Python code.
코드도 할 수 있는 함수요
And then we're going to sort of give that to the LLM and say, okay, you can use this.
그런 다음 그걸 LLM에 주고 이걸 사용하라고 하는 거죠
You can run this software on my computer in some way.
내 컴퓨터로 이 소프트웨어를 작동시켜요
It sounds sounds mysterious.
신비롭게 들리네요
It sounds a bit spooky, really.
비트가 좀 으스스하네요
Uh, but alas, it is not.
하지만 그렇지 않아요
Not that clever.
별로 안 똑똑해요
It's a pretty simple workflow around it.
워크플로우는 아주 간단해요
Here's the scoop.
특종이에요
What we do is we start by defining what functions we have available that the LM is allowed to call.
LM이 호출할 수 있는 사용 가능한 함수를 정의하는 것부터 시작하죠
So we define these functions.
이 함수들을 정의하죠
Let's say we have a calculator.
계산기가 있다고 가정해 보죠
We define the calculator.
계산기는 정의했어요
We say what are the inputs, what kind of outputs and when should the LM use it.
입력과 출력은 무엇인지 LM이 언제 사용해야 하는지도요
And then we tell the LM about that.
달 착륙선에 그 얘기를 하는 거죠
When we make a call to do something we say to it, hey, can you can you respond to this user.
뭔가를 하려고 호출할 때 사용자에게 응답할 수 있는지 묻죠
And by the way, you have access to this tool.
이 도구에 엑세스할 수 있어요
When the LM replies to us, it can either just respond with a prompt or it can respond with something
LM이 응답할 때 프롬프트로 응답할 수도 있고 혹은 다른 것으로 응답할 수도
like, hey, if I'm going to to to generate you a response, first I'm going to need to ask you to run
있습니다 응답을 생성해야 한다면 먼저 당신이 말한 도구를 실행하도록
that tool you told me about and run it with these inputs and then provide me back with the outputs.
요청해야 합니다 입력으로 실행하고 출력을 제공해야 하죠
And then you take that, you run the tool and then you provide the responses back to the LM, and it
그걸 가져가서 도구를 실행하고 LM에 응답을 다시 제공하면 LM은 응답을 생성하는
then uses it to generate its response.
데 사용하죠
So if you follow my drift there, it's not actually particularly amazing.
제 말을 이해하신다면 사실 그렇게 대단하진 않아요
It's that you call an LM and it responds and says, hey, I need you to call the tool that you told
LM을 호출하면 응답이 옵니다 당신이 갖고 있다고 한 도구를 호출해
me you have.
주세요
You do that, you provide it back to the LM, and then it's able to give you richer responses.
그렇게 하면 LM에 다시 제공됩니다 그럼 더 풍부한 반응을 제공하죠
And if you're really following along, you'll realize that that's not massively different to the kind
잘 따라오신다면 지난 랩에서 했던 것과 크게 다르지 않다는
of thing we did in the last lab when we just looked for a string and we just inserted extra context
걸 아실 겁니다 문자열을 찾아 프롬프트에 추가 컨텍스트를 삽입해 LM으로
in the prompt that goes to the LM, it's just about really inserting extra context in prompts.
간 거요 프롬프트에 추가 컨텍스트를 삽입하는 거죠
All right.
좋아요
Anyway, hopefully I didn't muddle you there, but it's going to come together when you see the code,
어쨌든 헷갈리신 게 아니면 좋겠네요 코드를 보시면 다 이해될 거예요
I promise you.
약속드리죠
But first, what are the use cases.
먼저 유스 케이스가 뭐죠?
When when do we typically do this.
보통 언제 이걸 하죠?
There are four ones that really that you come across a lot.
자주 보게 되는 게 네 가지 있어요
Um, you can use tools to fetch extra data, like look something up in a database, um, add knowledge.
도구를 이용해 추가 데이터를 가져올 수도 있어요 데이터베이스에서 찾아보고 지식을 추가하는 것처럼요
Uh, and again, you can think of it that's rather similar to what we did with with belts in the last
지난 랩에서 벨트랑 했던 것과 비슷하다고 생각하실
lab, but you can do that using tools instead.
수 있지만 대신 도구를 사용할 수 있어요
Uh, you can use it as a way that the LM can take an action, like booking a meeting, so you can tell
LM이 행동을 취하는 방법으로 사용할 수 있습니다 회의를 예약하는 것처럼요 그럼
it as part of your, uh, you have access.
액세스 권한의 일부로 말할 수 있죠
You have the ability to actually, uh, to carry out these, these, these items to buy a plane ticket
실제로 이런 물건을 운반할 능력이 있고 비행기 표를 사서 다음 일을
to do, do the following.
할 수 있어요
Um, and essentially in its response back, it will tell you that that's the tool that wants to use,
기본적으로 응답을 보면 사용하고 싶은 툴이 뭔지 알려줍니다 방금
as I just mentioned, a use case would be a calculator.
언급한 것처럼요 사용 사례는 계산기예요
Uh, LMS are famously not great at calculations because all they're trying to do is predict, uh, tokens
LMS는 계산에 약하기로 유명하죠 영어로 토큰을 예측하는 게 전부니까요
They don't have, like, a calculator built in to a to a deep neural network.
심층 신경망에 계산기가 내장돼 있지 않아요
But you can provide that as a tool.
하지만 도구로 제공할 수 있어요
And you can notice that, uh, GPT four is very good at calculations these days.
보시다시피 GPT 4는 요즘 연산에 아주 능숙하죠
And one wonders whether something that's going on behind the scenes might be something like this, that
배후에서 일어나는 일이 이런 건 아닌지 궁금하네요 계산을
it might have its own tool made available in order to run calculations.
실행하기 위해 고유한 도구를 사용할 수 있는 거죠
Perhaps just speculation, but it seems very reasonable.
추측일 수도 있지만 아주 합리적인 것 같아요
Another thing it can do is modify the UI so you could tell it, hey, here's some tools.
UI 수정도 할 수 있어요 여기 도구가 있다고 말할 수 있게요
You can use, some functions you can call that will update different things on my user interface.
사용자 인터페이스에서 다양한 걸 업데이트하는 함수를 사용할 수 있어요
And that would give the LLM the direct ability to trigger changes in the UI, which is a pretty cool
LLM은 UI에서 변화를 촉발하는 직접적인 기능을 갖게 됩니다 LLM과 UI 사이에
idea to have sort of tighter integration between the LLM and the UI.
더 탄탄한 통합을 갖는다는 건 멋진 아이디어죠
Again, one thing worth pointing out for the second one here, and for the fourth one for taking actions
두 번째에 대해 짚고 넘어갈 게 하나 있어요 네 번째 것은 행동을 취하고 UI 수정하는
and modifying the UI, there will be another way to achieve this.
거죠 이걸 달성할 다른 방법이 있어요
That would be perhaps a simpler approach if that's all you wanted to do.
그게 당신이 원하는 전부라면 더 간단한 방법이겠죠
See if you can, based on something we've already done before, uh, give you a moment to pause, to
전에 했던 걸 바탕으로 잠시 멈춰서 제가 뭘 하려는지
think about what I might be getting at.
생각해 보세요
The answer is, you remember, uh, in one of the earlier labs we had the model respond in JSON to respond
답은 이거죠 초기 실험 중 하나에서 JSON에서 모델이 구조적 응답으로 응답하게 한 거
with a structured response, and its response had JSON to tell us bits of information.
기억하시죠? 그 응답은 JSON이 정보를 제공했고요
In our case, it was about links and uh, giving us more information about fully qualified links and
저희의 경우는 링크가 중요했어요 완전한 자격의 링크와 수집할 링크에 대한 정보를
which links to collect.
더 많이 주는 거였죠
Well, similarly, we could just ask the model to respond in JSON with what actions need to be taken
유사하게 모델에게 JSON에서 반응하도록 요청할 수도 있어요 회의를 예약하기 위해 어떤 행동을 취해야 하는지
to book a meeting or respond in JSON based on how it wants the user interface modified.
또는 JSON에서 반응해야 하는지 사용자 인터페이스를 어떻게 수정하길 원하는지에 근거해서요
So there are other ways other than using tools to accomplish this.
도구를 사용하는 것 외에 다른 방법도 있어요
But if you want to be able to give it tools in addition to streaming back text, then this is a good
하지만 스트리밍 백 텍스트 외에 도구를 제공하고 싶다면 이게 좋은 해결책이에요
That's the that's the best time to use this when it's in conjunction with a number of other things that
그게 이걸 사용하기에 가장 좋은 때죠 LM이 작업하는 다른 여러 가지 작업과
the LM is doing.
함께요
So these tools are sort of adding to its capabilities.
이런 도구들이 기능에 추가되는 거죠
So what we're going to do now is build an informed airline customer support agent.
이제 할 일은 항공사 고객 지원 에이전트를 정보에 따라 만드는 거죠
We're going to want to be able to tell it that we're traveling to Paris and then have it respond with
우리가 파리로 간다고 말하고 파리행 비행기 표 가격으로 답장을
a ticket price to Paris.
받아야 해요
That's the idea.
그게 목적이죠
We're going to do it with tools, and I will see you over in the lab to find out how.
도구를 이용해 알아보겠습니다 실험실에서 방법을 알아보죠